<data date-time-format="iso8601">
    <event start="1877-01-23" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/TheLevantHerald+1877">Levant Herald 23 Jan 1877 (vol.IX, #14)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;From an occasional correspondent at Mersin  Report from Tarsus that the 2.000 recruits garrisoned in the city receive a daily pay of 60 para (i.e. Ps 1"20) in caime lira, which is not accepted by money changers and shop owners. Hence, troops start looting in demand for food. &lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1878-03-21" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/thamarat+151a">Thamarāt 21 Mar 1878 (#151)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;20 Mar 1878 [16 Rab I]  "Some days ago , the quarantine doctor of this place. from the village of qābūn about an hour's distance from Damascus, sent his son to his house in Damascus to settle necessities. As he had not returned until the morning of the second day, he sent some of his relatives who told him that he did not reach Damascus. They received  tumultuous ideas. and they informed the authorities about that and a search commenced that found him [?] without a passenger ... The investigation is headed by  , binbaşı of the Ḍabṭiyya of the centre of the province and the deputy of the Amīr Alāy." some other gentlemen named  They found him murdered in the house of one of the villagers of . The responsible men were arrested and sent to prison. The Majlis al-tamyīz is currently investigating the case. and the reasons for his murder.  ON THE FOOD RIOTS IN DAMASCUS  It is said that the reason is his relation with a woman from the women of the village. But the unknown truth is when ....  for two days congregated a crowd of poor women (ijtamaʿa jamīʿ al-fuqarāʾ min al-nisāʾ) most of whom were the wives of the Redif and Mustaḥfiẓ troops. They went to the Serai (bāb al-ḥukūma) raising their voices and howling on the account of a shortage of bread and sent a loaf of bread to the Vali and he found it [xxx] to be of a black nature or of a bad smell and in this situation he issued a [his] strict order to the head of the municipality and the aforementioned .  [xxx] with the help of  and  some houses of wheat hoarders (buyūt muḥtakirī al-qamḥ) were inspected. They extracted an ample amount of wheat (khinṭa) that was brought to the serai. and a number of bakers was shown around on the streets shackled. The bread improved by those means in a way that made the community praise the Vali [very long exclamation to this end] &lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1878-03-21" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/thamarat+151">Thamarāt 21 Mar 1878 (#151)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;13 Mar 1878  - admin changes  - situation of the poor: the women and children, who are disabled / deprived of those who were sent to the theatres (dār al-ḥarb) and who are not relieved from the strain of hardship. particularly for the poor, who do not have any bread. as the prices of wheat and bread are dear. the poor cannot afford the raṭl of bread, the black quality of which is sold at Ps3. the bitterness at the night of parting with the thickness/ply of the bakers, their .... in poverty from which they are not relieved and nothing being done.  - thus today, some of them (baʿḍahum, i.e. not necessarily the women only) went to the municipal council with the goal of obtaining a Ps1 subsidy for every raṭl of bread ... what is consumed of the kaime [i.e. reduced in value] as it is said 'there is no power nor might but in God'.  - fate of the refugees is even worse.&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1878-03-27" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/Jago+1878e">PRO FO 78/2850 Damascus political 5, Jago to Earl of Derby, 27 Mar 1878&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;The copy of this report can be found in FO 226/197  and Fo 195/1201  - social conditions after the war, bread riot on March 16&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1878-03-27" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/Jago+1878l">PRO FO 226/197 Damascus Political 5, Jago to Earl of Derby,  <em xmlns:bachf="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:w="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/wordprocessingml/2006/main" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" style="font-style:italic">State of Affairs in Damascus</em>, 27 Mar 1878&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;that is the actual report on "The state of affairs in Damascus" including the bread riots on March 16th 1878, when women stormed the serail.  original to be found in FO 78/2850  Political No. 5    Vice Consul Jago  to The Earl of Derby    Dam.s March 27. 1878    My Lord, I have the honor to report to Y.L. that recent events having prepared the people for what is considered by them as tantamount to the collapse of Ottoman power, the news of the signing  of peace between Russia &amp; Turkey has been received here with comparative indifference.    To the small Christian and Jewish communities which have unscathed [?] out of the ordeal just past through cave in occasional  panics and in the heavy pecuniary losses - incidental to commercial stagnation and  governmental indebtedness , the news has affoured belief from the fears generated by the war, besides hopes, too vague to to be put into shape, of some amelioration of their present position.    Among the better &amp; more affluent classes of the Moslems, few as they now are, whose means have enabled them to escape     conscription if not the payment of heavy war taxation, the little sympathy which before existed with the ruling Power, springing solely out of identity of religion, has been totally extinguished by the bitter recollection  of sacrifies unstinlingly [?] wrung from the country, and which now, owing, as they assert to Turkish corruption &amp; incapacity have proved wholly in vain.    To the poorest classes of the Moslem population of the settled districts which, whether urban or rural, have borne the entire brunt of the large levies made in Syria - (estimated by the military authorities at 115000 men from the  Vilayets of Syria &amp; Aleppo) - and have been besides reduced to semi starvation by the forcible abstraction of bread-winners, by war and other taxes ruthlessly levied, and by the  capacity of any army of unpaid officials, no relief is apparent. They have given their all in men &amp; money; &amp; then ignorance &amp; distress preclude  them from entertaining hopes for the future    even were such more apparent then they are.    A strong disaffection against Ottoman rule pervades all classes of the Moslems but is only manifested in words. Leaders they have none. The energies of the lower classes are absorbed in eking out a bare subsistence as best they can; while the better classes bent upon preserving the little the still possess, are sunk in despondency at the prospect before them and are fain to seek consolation in the feelings of resignation peculiar to their faith.    Those few who by reason of their wealth, or by their position in the religious hierarchy, are still deemed leaders, or, more properly, the heads of the people, are united only by the bond of common dislike to a  government to the corruption and general departure from the strict tenets of Islam of which, they seek to ascribe all the evils which have overtaken the country.    Resistance, however, passive or otherwise, to the bewests of God, in the matters of    civil authority where their joint action is demanded in order to regularize governmental [...] or local exactions, is defeated by the petty rivalries &amp; jealousies which of all times and under all circumstances exist among them to a degree to render them useless as protectors of the common interests of the people, and impotent when considered as a  possible element of danger to the Ruling Power.    This general feeling of discontent &amp; disaffection against every thing Ottoman -  proceeding out of recent events, shored itself forcibly on the 16.th instant &amp; following days  when owing to a rise in the already high price of bread, a mob of women, chiefly the families of departed Radifs, stormed the Seraïl of Damascus, the official residence of Djevdet Pasha, the newly appointed Gov.r Gen. of Syria.    Bitter curses upon the Sultan &amp; his Gov.t for the evils which have lately fallen  upon the land were liberally showered upon the Pasha, as well as allusions    to the corruption of the administration in  general and of Governors General in particular.    Reproaches for the losses of their male relatives were interspersed with hopes from the more desperate that the Russians would take Syria &amp; thus relieve them from  the curse upon them.    These sentiments are the echo of public opinion in Damascus expressing itself in a manner peculiar to the people.    Displays of fanatical temper towards Christians during Turkish successes, slight as they were owing to the vigilance of the Commander in Chief in compelling the action of the Police, ceased with the news of the reverses; and past &amp; present sufferings combined with the uncertainty of future relief seem to have eradicated, for the present at least, any tendency to assume a superiority, formerly believed in by the bigoted and ignorant and often worked upon by interested parties, but now under    the pressure of actual circumstances tacitly abandoned.    The Christians &amp; Jews of Syria have escaped in a high degree the evils which have so disastrously pressed upon their less favored Moslem brethren. Moral pressure alone has been use in respect of the never ending so called voluntary war taxes so ruthlessly levied upo the Moslems; &amp; the quota they have subscribe has been out of all proportion to what they have been asked for. In fact  what they have given has simply been to save appearances.    The Civil administration of the Vilayet since the beginning of the war has existed only in name. Corruption &amp; administrative [...] have been glaring even for Syria &amp; seem to have increased in inverse proportion to the reverser of the Turkish arms. And although the virtual stoppage of pay of employes has no doubt much to answer for, it can hardly be held     as a sufficient excuse for the unblushing manner n which the necessities of the people arising out of war burdens, and  Imperial Interests, have been trade upon for personal profit by the officials of this Province, high &amp; low, to the detriment of the Gov.t in its hour of need and to the grinding &amp; impoverishment of all those whose lack of position or means failed  to protect them.    Orders have been received from Constantinople to disband the Mustafiz now under arms. Execution, however, has been suspended pending the return of regular troops to Syria. The force of regular troops kept here during the war has been 2 battalions of Infantry; one at Dam.s &amp; the other disposed of throughout the Province to serve as the backbone for raw and aged local levies. Besides  theses are the mounted Zaptiehs or Rural Police numbering nominally    1800 men, but really, owing to non- payment of wages, about 900 effectives. This small force has sufficed to preserve order, and to crush, without serious collision, inciffcent [?] attempts at resistance against governmental exigencies in  men or taxes of some of the more unruly of the inhabitants; and it shows forcibly  both the great prestige which the Ottoman Power still obtains as a repressive  agency in spie of its present situation, and the want of cohesion among the heterogenous elements composing the population of Syria.    Consular influence in this great Mohamedan centre was naturally  much restricted during the war by political events. The Corps was however  brought up to its full strength by the appointments of an Italian and of  Spanish Consul as well as of a German Vice Consul; although the little influence possessed by this British    Vice Consulate was perhaps not more  conspicuous than that of the agents of other Powers the far greater number of persons under its protection, and the importance of their suspending claims amounting in the aggrega to about £ 280,000, caused the inaction of the administration to be more severely felt by the British than by other nationalities.    Since the arrival the other day of Djevdet Pasha, the new Governor General, the machinery of the Civil Government has once more been set in motion &amp; as marked change  for the better, in respect of administration routine at least, is apparent.    Save the article of bread the necessaries of life are very cheap. The coming harvests promise to be unusually abundant. They will not, however, be available for    two months.    Damascus, the surrounding country, including the Hauran, continues to enjoy perfect tranquillity despite the general discontent &amp; the distress and I have been unable to discover any foundation for the disquieting though vague rumors which have recently appeared in the European Press regarding Syria.    I have [...] (signed) T.S. Jago V.Consul &lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1878-03-27" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/Jago+1878p">PRO FO 195/1201 Damascus political 5, Jago to Earl of Derby, 27 Mar 1878&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;The copy of this report can be found in FO 226/197  and FO 195/1201  - social conditions after the war, bread riot on March 16&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1878-03-28" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/TheLevantHerald+1878b">Levant Herald 28 Mar 1878 (vol.X, #73)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;A letter from Beirut Mar.18, reporting on the sinking of the vessel Sphinx with 3.000 Circassian refugees onboard in the waters of Cyprus. The author comments on the influx of these refugees in Syria and Beirut, where only 2.000 of them arrived. Finally he describes the situation at Damascus as devastating and that women stormed the palace in demand for bread.&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1878-03-29" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/TheLevantHerald+1878c">Levant Herald 29 Mar 1878 (vol.X, #74)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;A letter from Beirut Mar.18, reporting on the sinking of the vessel Sphinx with 3.000 Circassian refugees onboard in the waters of Cyprus. The author comments on the influx of these refugees in Syria and Beirut, where only 2.000 of them arrived. Finally he describes the situation at Damascus as devastating and that women gather daily underneath the windows of the palace in demand for bread.&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1878-04-11" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/TheLevantHerald+1878d">Levant Herald 11 Apr 1878 (vol.X, #85)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;"Le Hadikat-ul-Akhbar [ḥadīqat al-akhbār], journal official publié à Beyrouth, dit qu'une réunion d'indigents et de pauvres s'est tenue la semaine dernière devant le sérail du gouvernement à Damas, en faisant entendre des murmures et des plaintes contre la rareté du pain, la mauvaise qualité de celui livré à la consommation, jointe à l'excessive élévation du prix, et cela vu l'absence des céréales que des entrepreneurs avaient emmagasinées a qu'ils refusaient de livrer au marché. Le vali, Djevdet pacha, se rendit immédiatement au Conseil administratif et concerta les mesures nécessaires pour faire cesser cet état de choses. Les magasins du Méidan remplis de blé ont été ouverts au marché et les boulangers ont pu ainsi se fournier du blé qui leur était nécessaire et livrer à la consommation une bonne qualité de blé, à un prix relativement fort réduit."&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1880-03-16" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/thamarat+272a">Thamarāt 16 Mar 1880 (#272)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;BREAD RIOT IN BEIRUT:  "tamma baʿda an ʿalam al-khāṣṣ wa al-ʿāmm mādhā ḥadatha ʿalā al-nuqūd ..."  as all strata heard about the fate of the money, the poor helped themselves to bread when the bakeries and public ovens where closed on Friday morning. literally: the poor attacked (fa-hajamat al-ahālī min al-fuqarāʾ ʿalayhā) the closed bakeries and stores.  - Mutaṣarrif established exchange rates&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1908-08-21" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/lisan+5795a">Lisān 21 Aug 1908 (#5795)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;yesterday: bread riot in Beirut:Large numbers of poor and destitute gathered yesterday morning (ijtamaʿa awwal ams jumhūr kabīr min al-fuqarāʾ wa arbāb al-ʿayyāl) in front of the Serai in Beirut. They called for help and lamented  (yastaghīthūna wa yatawasilūna) the current situation and called for the lowering of prices of Ṭaḥīn and Bread to ease their suffering and those of all other poor, especially since most flour merchants, sellers of Ṭaḥīn, owners of ovens and bakeries (makhābiz) already tyrannise them and profit from sunflower bread (quwat al-ʿabād) in a clear breach of all laws and legal prescriptions (jamīʿ al-qawānīn wa al-sharāʾiʿ) until the raṭl of bread was sold at more then Ps 7,5. This is contrary to justice (al-ʿadāla) and no one can [possibly] accept this. When their [yelling of] complaints grew and their shouting and screaming  rose, the vigorous Anīs Efendi Ramaḍān, superintendent of the police, went out to meet them. He soothed their minds with a speech full of courtesy and refinement. He assured them that the authorities directed its zeal and efforts to the lowering of the bread prices / prices of foodstuffs (asʿār al-quwat) and thus they withdraw gratefully.Their agreement had almost held until they were met by a group of their likes (jamāʿat min amthālihim), wretched and poor (arbāb al-ʿayāl wa al-fuqarāh).Together they went to the customs demonstrating in the same manner as the last time, scattering the flour on the floor and preventing its export from the province and killing (yaftakūna) everyone who tried to stop them. Their threatening and menacing was not stopped until the director of the police and assured them of the seriousness of the [governments efforts] to secure the necessary funds and ease the price of food (al-maʾkūlāt). He explained everything and how it would take less than 10 days for the Ṭaḥīn calamity to ease as well as all other calamities that they complained of. And thus they were appeased.yesterday they again gathered (ijtimāʿ) and decided amongst them to repeat their demonstrations (muẓāharāt) today. Thus they roamed (yaṭūfū) the stores of flour (sāḥat al-qamḥ) and all other places where Ṭaḥīn is sold and they also demonstrated in expression of their dissatisfaction with the high prices of meat etc."- short statement on Lisā's position on the matter &lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1908-09-21" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/MajorRamsay+1908">PRO FO 371/560 Baghdad, Major Ramsay to Government of India, 21 Sep 1908&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt; (44/F37953/08)  Therapia 721, 27 Oct 1908, Lowther   "Wheat Riots at Baghdad, Major Bemsay’s No 864 reporting on"  Enclosing the despatch by the Consul General in Baghdad  #Inclosure no. 1  Bagdad, 21 Sep 1908, Major Ramsay to Government of India  "Sir,  In continuation of my letter [No. 847] dated the 14th instant, I have the honour to report that the telegram of which the purport was given in the third paragraph of that letter appears to have been malevolently added to in Bagdad before it was made partially public. The original telegram, as received from Constantinople, contained no reference to the use of military force against the Young Turk Committee in provincial towns. The perverted version of the telegram was made known in Karbala.  2. On the 16th instant there was a riot in which some of the grain stored were pillaged. The exportation of wheat has for some time been prohibited, and on the 14th and 15th instant it was rumoured that a certain Jew had received permission from Constantinople to export some wheat and that he was going to load it on the 16th. On that morning a crowd went to the Vali to protest. It is said that the Vali assured them that no order had been issued allowing the export of wheat, and it is said that the Vali strengthened his assurance by saying that when an attempt to load wad made it would time for the people to make serious complaints. It is not possible to know exactly what was said, much less what was understood, but the crowd went straight off to the grain stores and took what they could carry. It was at first reported that the loss was enormous, but the estimates have since been largely reduced, and I am inclined to think that the loss cannot have been very great. The populace took what it could during an interval of about an hour and a-half, but the entrances to the store are narrow and they were choked by the crowd, so much so that a number of the rioters found it convenient to pass their stolen wheat over the wall. In these circumstances a very large quantity of wheat cannot have been removed. Messrs. Lynch’s experience is that with the best arrangement, and all wheat in bags, not more than 100 tons could be removed in an hour and a-half. A very small proportion of this can have been taken by a struggling crowd.   One man claimed compensation for about 600l. [£ 600] worth of wheat which he said he held on behalf of a British subject and which he said had been pillaged during the riot. I went to his place of business to examine his books, and he then said that he did not want the intervention of the Consulate and would settle the matter himself.  Another man who claimed compensation on behalf of Messrs. Andrew Weir and Co. of London had to admit that he could not produce proof that any Court would accept.   A third man’s claim is still under consideration, but from what I have heard I am pretty fairly certain that it will not stand examination.  There is no doubt that all of these men have lost wheat, but they cannot prove that it was the property of British subjects.  3. There are a number of deserters about Bagdad who are a continual source of  danger to peaceful people. I understand that the Commander of the VIth Army Corps has written to Constantinople to say that it is necessary either to come to some settlement with them or to shoot them.  4. The Young Turk Committee at Karbala has made all the officials publicly swear loyalty to the Constitution, but the Mutessarif shows a strong dislike to interference, and the Vali of Bagdad is said to be troubled with many differences between the two parties.  I have, &amp;c. …&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1908-10-01" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/Devey+1908c">PRO FO 371/560 Damascus 51, Devey to Lowther,  <em xmlns:bachf="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:w="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/wordprocessingml/2006/main" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" style="font-style:italic">Quarterly Report</em>, 1 Oct 1908&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;(44/F37930/08)Therapia 697, 24 Oct 1908, Lowther to"Quarterly report on Damascus" Printed for considerationInclosure: Damascus 51, 1 Oct 1908, Devey to Lowther. Printed version &amp; type written version[…]"the great ‘coup d’Etat’ which took place in Turkey on the 24th July occupied all minds and arouses every emotion with the proclamation of the Constitution, in Damascus as in all other important centres in the Empire. Among its results worthy of remark here were (a) celebrations and festivities (b) dismissal or resignation of notoriously corrupt  officials (c) formation of clubs and associations (d) parliamentary elections (e) reforms in various governmental departments. (f) release or rehabilitation of political exiles or persons [xxx].Rejoicings and joyful manifestation are only coming now to an end, after lasting more than two months: more than 25 well organized great meetings were held int he different quarters of the city, mostly attended by several thousands [sic] demonstrators and spectators, and hundreds of speeches were delivered, all condemning autocracy as despotic &amp; tyrannical and eulogizing liberty and constitutional government. About £2000 were spent on the festivities and had not notables of Damascus with the young Turks lately recommended their cessation they might have continued for another month or more. It is to be remarked with pleasure that all these gathering &amp; demonstrations were conducted most orderly without any dispute or ill feeling among those who assembled.Many corrupt officials were either dismissed or withdrew themselves.The Alaybey of Gendarmerie, the Chief of Police, the Muhassebeji, six Caimacams of Cazas, Moh.d P. Adm [Muḥammad Pasha al-ʿAẓm] of Idara Mejliss with about 30 other minor officials vacated their posts, mostly to the general satisfaction of the public and it is debated now among ‘Young Turkey’ adherents whether it would be right to punish the officials who were led to bribery by the littleness of their pay &amp; its frequent irregularity. Doubtless the proper course will be followed in leaving this matter to the jurisdiction  of Parliament when it assembles, and the ignorious[?] dismissal of the more corrupt, rapacious &amp; outrageous among officials suffices for the moment. Moreover, the vacancies are not being easily filled up by really good substitutes, for such persons are at present  rare, and often unwilling to serve. Damascus Clubs &amp; associations, besides the Union &amp; Progress number now five viz Hurriyet, Ulema, Medical, Commercial, Free Ottoman besides a Shoemaker guild. the first two are showing much activity wh.[ich] is likely to excite mutation . The misapprehension &amp; with uncalled solicitude Ulema are anxious to comcure [?sic] &amp; uphold Islam against the liberal views of the Young Turks, while the latter have no intention at present to interfere with religious precepts. There is little record as to practical work effected [?] by other clubs though their moral influence cannot be other than good.The Parliamentary elections are under preparation the last two months and in some cazas the voters have already voted for the electors, but in Damascus city this process will begin in a week’s time. It is not even announced yet how many deputies will represent this Vilayet in the Parliament but it is supposed that they will be seven or eight. The Hauran people still reject their privilege to elect a deputy and the efforts of the government in dissuading them from this self-inflicted loss seem to be futile. The Mutessarif of Kerak lately resigned on grounds of health, but before doing so had been able to set going a local society or club for instruction of the people of his district who indeed are little  less backward &amp;ignorant than this of Hauran.The reforms in the various departments of the government proceed slowly. The Municipality suppressed most improperly awarded pensions paid to persons doing nothing for it  and succeeded in amassing about £3000 through various economies. The Public Instruction Department formed a new chamber to consider the reorganization of the educational system in this Vilayet. In the departments no special reforms worth mentioning have been introduced but many are being talked of &amp; discussed. The political exiles who had been releases or rehabilitated included many persons of rank, both military and civil. Mushir Fuad Pasha’s release was the occasion of great demonstrations in Damascus, but the rehabilitation of others, with a few exceptions, was not publicly noticed, for this disgraces persons were always enjoying personal freedom  and a very few persons knew that they were ‘Ikamet Mamours’ [iqāma maʾmūr]. The chief names among these were, Nouri P. Ferik of Cavalry, another Ferik called Nouri Pasha sent to live here without duties, Ferik Ibrahim Pasha (those three Feriks kept for Constantinople), Ferik Lt. Osman P., Liva Behjet Pasha (those two died recently), Colonel Bedri Bey (now of Liva Bedri P. in Constantinople). The Maàriz Mushiri [?] &amp; his assistant, and many minor officials or private persons; such as members of the Bedr Khan family, numbering more than a hundred. Further as reported in desp. No. 32, the Ismailians subjected to religious persecution were pardoned. Happily no sort of disorder or riotous intention was displayed here for the purpose of releasing prisoners and ordinary criminals generally, as took place in some other places."Ḥijāz railway was completed in seven years and inaugurated on 1 Sep 1908. four of the five battalions employed for earthworks on the line were allowed to return to their garrisons. "about 1400 of these battalions on expiry of service were disbanded. Moreover, the four battalions of the 40th Reg, sent to Medina from this Army Corps in June last, to guard the line, are also ordered back to their headquarters. At present only two battalions are to be kept there to take care of the line as regards repairs &amp; protection." No aspirations to commence construction beyond Medina due to increasing Bedouin raids "Public security in the Vilayet has been during the quarter satisfactory and order was properly kept. The Bedouins have been quiet &amp; peaceful during the summer, and only on two or three occasions made petty rais &amp; drove or carried away animals or goods but the spoils were restored to their owners without great difficulties." Druze and Bedouins seem under the spell of the government and calmly wait for the implementation of the promised reforms"the crops this year were in general very good and the grain harvest in most of the districts of the Province was exceptionally abundant. The apricot produce was above the average while walnuts were much below. All prices of fruit and cereals are still high and the peasants this year will do well. An exception might be mentioned as  as regards locusts which made a perceptible damage in the Kalamoun district but had a very slight effect in some other Cazas. But the loss to the Vilayet in general has been small.As respects trade, no special remarks need be made; strikes at Beirut at the Customs and on local railways have produced only exiguous loss here. With reference to the latter we may note that public opinion judges that the smaller employés  were underpaid, while the profits of the Company &amp; of its directors were considerable and the public at the same time ill served.Public health has been satisfactory on the whole this summer, but the Ain Fijeh water has not been received the general approbation anticipated which is to be regretted, as theres is absolute proof the it is the best &amp; purest spring water of al this neighbourhood. Its distribution to all quarters of the city proceeds slowly."&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-06-23" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/lisan+6359">Lisān 23 Jun 1910 (#6359)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;Aleppo, al-taqaddum: - BREAD RIOT: extremely dear prices of cereals. the shunbul of flour sold at Ps 170 [possibly misprint, should be Ps 70] and today it is at Ps 80. this is due to hoarding. a certain ʿAbd al-Raḥmān Efendi Jasir bought a large quantity of flour and  in result the prices hiked to Ps 120. A large crowd then formed and attacked the latter's store.  etc.&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-07-03" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/jarmuq+412a">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 3 Jul 1910 (#412)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;Yesterday forenoon gathered crowds of women (katharat jumūʿ al-nisāʾ) in front of the Serai, howling and shouting in their opposition (shākiyyāt) to the very high bread prices. Announcing their points with cries and howls. In the morning the callers/ announcers (munād) had been circling the city inviting the people (al-nās) to the gathering (ijtimāʿ) and stirring the emotions about their situation being effected by the steep increase of prices. Within an hour the streets were packed, with the women leading [the demonstration] and the men behind them as a backup force / like to force of the noon (ka-quwwat al-ẓahr). As the authorities (ḥukūma) became wary/afraid of the developments, their asked for the support of soldiers. Some of their officers commanded the law enforcement troops (al-ḍabṭ wa al-rabṭ) to check/meet those crowds (jumūʿ) with force. Thanks to God that  they managed to disperse them through threatening, light beating, and occasional sloshing of water from the pump. Then they returned/retreated and nothing resulted from this [event] but the insult and abuse of some grain (ṭaḥīn) traders in town.  The provincial administration already mailed the sancaks of Hamah and Ḥawrān to send all their wheat stores [to Damascus] and to Beirut to supply its stores of flour.  The municipality set the price (saʿʿrat) for a raṭl of good bread to Ps3"30 and took measures against (ḍarabat ʿalā īday man …) those grain traders and millers who attempted to impose a monopoly. Likewise the province issued firm instructions to the Ḥawrān to prevent/ban Damascene traders and others from buying the wheat from its fields and transporting it to destinations other than Damascus, as had been their custom for the last years.  Thus, yesterday, the price for a bushel of good wheat reached Ps53 and is expected to fall further during these two days when new cereals arrive on the market.&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-07-04" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/jarmuq+413">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 4 Jul 1910 (#413)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;3hd, a person from Mīdān wrote to them about the neglect of the municipality towards cleaning the streets and alleys from rubbish and thus the neglect of public health  hd, some intellectuals are of the opinion that prices of cereals would decrease if the authorities hurried the collection of the tithe and thus forced the peasants to sell their stocks. we will watch further developments  hd, yesterday: the Vali invited the dignitaries and the notables of the town to the lobby (ردهة) of the Serai and after informing them that the people (ahālīn) have the right to gather and to demand their right of petition guaranteed by the law, he explained them what results from such gatherings (ijtimāʿ) as the one the day before: harm/distress to the homeland (iḍrār ʿalā al-waṭan), because it was not legal and that they were responsible. meaning being that they are the notables of the land (bilād) and its heads and it must be their desire to counsel the people (al-ahālīn) in a language (lisān) they understand that it is not advisable to rep at their actions. and they answered his question. in the same way he gathered the Imāms (īmat) of the quarters and their mukhtars and stressed his point accordingly.  - he also wrote yesterday to various areas calling on them to deliver wheat and suggested to ban the export of any products that could secure the daily livelihood (ḥajiyyāt) of Dam. and thus the issue is possible peacefully concluded.  hd, informed that this year's harvest in the Ḥawrān yielded much less than last year's and that the Ḥawrānese called on the authorities to lower the  tithe from 25.000 kile of wheat to 15.000 ... authorities did not yield to this demand. circassian officials are ordered to enforce the tithe  hd, yesterday arrived the Hahambashi of Istanbul, received with all due honours by the authorities and his community [full note]&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-07-05" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/lisan+6369">Lisān 5 Jul 1910 (#6369)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;(wrongly marked as 2 Jul in my photos)Damascus:  - BREAD RIOT: the prices of flour and wheat are very high and the poor are destitute. The women gathered in front of the Serai, shouting and howling in critique of the prices of bread and flour, carrying small boys and infant girls on their arms as if they [...زغب القطا]. Barkers circled the streets of Damascus, stirring the emotions of the people (al-nās) about their situation being effected by the steep increase of prices. The populace (al-qawm) became aroused until [the authorities] became afraid by the developments and soldiers commenced to disperse the crowds (jamʿahum), with shouting, light beating, and water from the pump. And they retreated after shouting insults and ... to the grain (ṭaḥīn) sellers and called on God to deliver them from the tyranny of those monopolists.  - the province wrote to Hamah, Ḥawrān, and Beirut to send whatever supplies of wheat they have and the municipality fixed the price of a raṭl of good bread at Ps 3"30 and fought the hoarders and monopolisers. further the mutaṣarrif of the Ḥawrān was informed that Damascene traders are prohibited from buying [sic] wheat. thus the price fell and already reached Ps 53 for a kile of nice wheat and the hope is that it will decrease further.  - its not only Damascus, which is hit by high prices and evil monopolists. those are damned who do not have any compassion for the poor and who do not fear the day of atonement   - Beirut is equally hit during the last two days and the poor suffer and critique is rife. The authorities do not comply with their duty and the evildoers remain unpunished. calling on the authorities to quell them with an iron fist. the poor have exhausted their blood and the conscience of the populace died (wa hum qawm qad mātat ḍamāʾirahum). and they lament to god.  - it is weird that the province of Syria wrote to Beirut to send all its stores to Damascus&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-07-05" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/jarmuq+414">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 5 Jul 1910 (#414)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;- joy and sorrow of the people depend on the authorities but they cannot met out happiness to the governed (maḥkūm) if they cannot provide what the people demand from every government:  security, justice (ʿadl), and a smooth way of earning a livelihood   - if one compares the current condition of this country with the state of affairs a decade ago. commodities are not as readily available as demanded and the government must open opportunities to supply livelihood (al-maʿash) to the people. distribute the profits from investment in its resources. equally the inhabitants must work quickly, for, if the basis of livelihood are not available, the people will flee the country or live in poverty. this is clear from historians and judges …  - the agricultural produce increased manifold, but the number of inhabitants increased even quicker.   - industrial output and fortunes increased, but the prices of daily necessities (ḥajiyyāt) rose even quicker. the work that supplied the livelihood ten years ago was waged with Ps 3; now it is Ps10 in towns and Ps7-8 in villages. to such an extend increased the prices of livelihood (maʿisha), and only a few craftsmen receives sufficient enough wages  - the madd of wheat had cost about Ps10 ten years ago and today it is sold at Ps 20-25. the condition of the peasant is the yardstick of the commoners fortunes ...  - but without doubt the urban workers are the most unfortunate as the salary for their work has increased to the same extend as the prices . and particularly the textile workers in Homs and Damascus suffered additionally from the dominance of European goods on the market.   - the task of the authorities is to ease the live of the people (al-nās) and not just regarding the issue of high prices of daily supplies criticised by the poor: easing the means of transport as the shall be prevented / forbidden from increasing the price of flour and bread. for instance, the tariff for 1 ton of flour on the Hijaz railway should be decreased, this would provide the peasants with the means to sell cereals to pay the tithe and the market would be supplied with sufficient amounts. prices will fall  - customs on cereal imports shall be lifted   - all what is demanded from the government for the success of its people (shaʿbihā) is to provide the basis of security and tranquility and ....  - and not the futility of telling the baker and the miller to sell at such and such a price and they then sell the wheat at dear prices, because otherwise they would have to cease work and thus the unhappiness will even be increased. rather the authorities should ban the merchants from hoarding and monopolising&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-07-12" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/Devey+1910b">PRO FO 371/1002 Damascus 28, Devey to Lowther,  <em xmlns:bachf="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:w="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/wordprocessingml/2006/main" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" style="font-style:italic">Quarterly Report</em>, 12 Jul 1910&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;May: Vali absent for about 5 weeks on tour of inspection to the south.   - The mushīr ʿUthmān Fawzī Pasha, currently on leave of absence to Constantinople, will return in ten days and it is rumoured that he will be appointed Vali and commander of the 5th Army. this would please the people of Syria and the inhabitants of Damascus   - "For it would seem that under the present administration much odium is being accumulated both against the vali and his officials, whilst the antagonistic sentiment as between Arab and Turk has been greatly fomented during the past three or four months now, whether by hasty or somewhat automatic behaviour on the part of office holders, or by their occasionally contemptuous or discourteous manners rewards local notables, or by the over-advanced views of those connected with the Young Turks’ party, who are manifesting themselves (not alone here in Syria, I imagine) in a distance tendency towards xenophobe.  The antagonistic sentiment between Turk and Arab is beginning to permeate downwards to the lower classes; and will soon be no longer confined to the ellema [ʿulamāʾ], notables and grandees, and official circles.  The most sore point of all is the attempt of Young Turks to propagate the use of Turkish in exclusion of Arabic in all official circles; and while all verbal evidence is in Arabic at the law courts, judgements, sentences, decrees, and sundry orders are put into Turkish often to the confusion of the applicant or litigant. In the Judicial Department again most of the higher officers such as the Procureur-General, Presidents of Courts, know scarcely any Arabic or indeed none at all, and, in fact, out of some thirty or more only about one-half a affair colloquial knowledge of the language of the country, these being mainly the clerks and assessors; of the three Mustantiks, one knows very little Arabic, whereas it is absolutely essential for his investigation.  The chauvinistic feelings of "Young Turkey" were somewhat stirred by the uncertain state of affairs in Crete no doubt, and that the tone of the native local press is sharing in the general vaguely expressed anti-foreign felling may be deduced from occasional remarks and opinions published; just this same moment some bite animad versions are being brought out in respect of the administration of Egypt."  - CONFLICT: confiscation of the bell at a British church school; refusal of authorities to let  of Zahle exercise  jurisdiction in Zabadani, gave grave offense to the Greek Orthodox Patriarchate  - mid-Apr: two days unofficial visit of Prince and Princess Eitel Friedrich  - mid-Apr: Bishop Blyth of Jerusalem held confirmation at St. John’s church  - 20 May: memorial service for King Edward at St. John’s  - 16 Apr: half a battalion dispatched to Beirut in consequence of disturbances there. many troops moved to the countryside around Damascus  - Bedouins and Druze clashing in the Hawran  - AGRICULtURE: satisfactory wheat and barley harvests, ca. 15-20 % less though than last year. "Price still rule high, for the grain merchants wished to hold their stocks as long as possible; this led to some petty disturbance in the nature of bread riots at the end of last month (here at Damascus almost exactly as at Aleppo); the merchants were at once compelled to release a portion of their stores, and prices fell for the time being though they remain high."  - apricots and fruits  - INDUSTRIES: glass factory mentioned in his last annual report: merchants bought land and "are beginning to erect buildings; and also a foreign undertaking for artificial ice. All is now ready for its production, but it seems there is little difficulty as to the furnishing of the Ain-FIjeh spring-water for the purpose at the last moment."  - AYN FIJA: the Egyptian contractor Fāris Rahbeh [Raḥība] had to declare bankruptcy as, having completed the works, the municipality only paid £T1.500 out of a bill of £T14.000.   - MUNICIPALITY: "As sequel to the above scandal three weeks ago, the whole municipality resigned office in a body. There have now been four presidents (Reis Belediyye) in the last six months, viz, Munir Effendi Yakub, Ahmed Hassibi, Hussein Bey, and the last appointed Ghalib Bey el-Zalik [, , , and ]. Faris Effendi Khouri [], lately Dragoman of this consulate, is a member of the new council, and serves on it with zeal and activity."  - Rumours that the Khedive will buy up all the imperial domains in Aleppo, Syria, Konia, and Aidin  - ten days ago: the Chief Rabbi of the OE, Hayim Nahum, arrived on his tour of inspection from Jerusalem  - Ruwela tribe  - "A German cavalry subaltern and rittmeister has just come here to instruct the Turkish cavalry either here or at Aleppo. Commandant Noirot is still absent at Beirout engaged in teaching the gendarmerie there or in the Lebanon.  - The Damascus members of the ‘Medjliss Meebusan’ [Senate] returned from their session at the close of last month and beginning of this, and among those who were received with a warm welcome and ovation were Shefik Bey Muayad [], Abdur-Rahman Bey [], and Rushdi Bey Shama []."&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-07-30" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/bashir+1974">Bashīr 30 Jul 1910 (#1974)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;wheat between Beirut and Damascus, muqtabas  - letter from province of Beirut to Dam complaining that the ban on export had caused a price hike and asking for it to be lifted. the provincial administrative council replied asking how much was imported and at which price before they could consider lifting the ban.   - provincial administrative council said that Beirut is not the worst hit city, as the province of Damascus had to disperse the desperate poor, destitute of any cereals, from its own Serai through the use of force and soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-08-13" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/muqtabas+161-eap">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 13 Aug 1910 (#446)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;1  al-umma taʿlimu nafsihā; by Muḥammad Kurd ʿAlī  1-2  Drūz Ḥawrān  2  hd: yest; 4 battalions and a number of canons arrived from Constantinople on their way to the Ḥawrān to fight the Druze rebellion  hd: wed night: , commander of the Ḥawrān campaign (al-ḥamla al-ḥawrāniyya) in Damascus  hd: further donors and donations for sending some students to Europe  hd: the directorate of Awqāf in Damascus shortly issues an iʿāne for the repair of the al-Madrasa al-Murādiyya  of at lest £T1.400 in order to again make it into a house of learning and knowledge  3  hd: attack of Druze and Bedouin brigands in the Jabal Ḥawrān (hajama ashqiyāʾ al-durūz wa ʿurbān al-jabal ʿalā …)  "a day in Ḥamā" (yawm fī ḥamāh): on the bread riots in Hama &lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-08-14" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/jarmuq+447a">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 14 Aug 1910 (#447)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;2hd, heavily increased prices of cereals caused riots in Hamah, attacking stores [as in Aleppo but NOT IN DAM]  3hd, yesterday: some poor in Homs followed the Hama example attacking some stores and ovens&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-08-14" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/muqtabas+162-eap">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 14 Aug 1910 (#447)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;1-2Drūz Ḥawrān  hd: report on a visit to al-Qaddam where the troops assemble on their way to the Ḥawrān&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-08-17" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/jarmuq+450">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 17 Aug 1910 (#450)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;last Sat: large crowd of poor assembled in Homs in protest agains high prices, &lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-08-20" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/jarmuq+452a">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 20 Aug 1910 (#452)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;by A.K. from Hamah: those who had looted wheat were arrested ...&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1910-08-21" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/jarmuq+453b">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 21 Aug 1910 (#453)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;truth about the "Homs incident", by Aḥmad Kurd ʿAlī from Homs: when the people of Homs heard about the looting (nahab), which had taken place in Ḥamāh, the minds of some of the mob / riffraff (raʿāʿ) picked up on the idea. violence broke out last Sat morn in the East of the city. thousands of poor people  besieged the serai and then attacked (hajamū) the Tripoli coach road company. gates were locked, but the mob threw stones at the officials …  - &lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1911-05-29" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/muqtabas+262-eap">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 29 May 1911 (#689)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;2  hd: on the prostitution affair at the Hotel Italy  - Muqtabas calls for moral improvement of the town and not the expulsion of the girls!  The police administration suspended acting on legal provisions against the Hotel "funduq dhāk al-īṭālī" on Marja Square, which shelters a group of prostitutes (mūmisāt) expelled from their homes in its dance hall. due to a vague decision of the provincial administration council, upon which we had reported, to evacuate them. the administration is looking for a location and inquired at the Vali in Kerak through letters, whether they need female workers there. he issued orders to prevent anybody from entering the place until everybody inside has left.  Do we cheer the authorities for their action?  allegedly the Vali's answer arrived today but we don't think to find the aspired solution in it. …  we hope that he decides against the government paying the owner of the place  or anybody else for the supervision of the women. they should return to the original dwellings until the authorities have found a solution to provide them with a living beyond dancing (al-marqaṣ).   the legal prescriptions are not close to places of worship and the silk factories (buyūt al-ḥarāʾir) they (the girls) have been expelled form. the pregnant [among them] have been released and moved to the houses of honourable people (ahl al-sharaf wa al-ʿirḍ).  they brought moral corruption (mafāsid) that blushes the face. therefore public opinion (al-raʾī al-ʿāmm) demands a hard hand against the transgressors to be administered by the authorities. similarly those of limited intellect. But Damascus won't be saved from moral corruption by removing these fallen girls / prostitutes (banāt al-hawā). the people call on the government to overdo and overstep the boundaries of its duties  hd: the inauguration of the railway between Tripoli and Homs will take in some days time  3  hd: it is said that the Vali of Syria will go to Medina after he leaves Kerak  hd: 16 men have been sentenced to three years imprisonment for their participation in the looting (nahab) in Ḥomṣ last year [i.e. the bread riot]. four of them are Christians, 12 are Muslims. five were actually imprisoned, the others are at large  4  iʿlān by the agency of the Ghar / Ghazz Yashām company  - moved from their old location in the Sancaḳdār road to a place opposite the municipality. signed by Fāris al-Khūrī &lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1911-07-13" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/Devey+1911c">PRO FO 618/3 Damascus Draft 38, Devey to Lowther,  <em xmlns:bachf="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:w="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/wordprocessingml/2006/main" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" style="font-style:italic">Quarterly Report</em>, 13 Jul 1911&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;"The past three months have been marked by punishments inflicted by Court Martial on about a hundred  Bedouins who revolted at Kerak last December of whom half a dozen were hanged."  Vali made 2 short tours of inspection: Ḥawrān and Jabal Druze; Maʿan, Kerak, and Salṭ  19 May,  returned, who had left for Constantinople on 7 Mar. made a short tour of the Druze areas  Quite mostly prevails throughout the province; some Bedouin "tricks" and riots at Hama  Emigration continuous unabated "from all parts of the district and without distinction of race or class, doubtless on account of conscription; even Jews of this city have been expatriating themselves. The Gov.t, it is to be explained, do not with to interpose any hindrance or check upon this impoverishment of the state preferring the principle of the individual's absolute liberty."  ADMIN CHANGES:  replaced  as Defterdar  Mufti had been appointed Qāḍī of Medina,  / Rudda Eff. was elected by large majority.   was elected to the provincial administration council and thus resigned as president of the municipality. no successor yet.  and  also elected to provincial administration council  Salṭ and maʿan  General Prosecutor  spent most time in Kerak investigating the Bedouin revolt. "Prison fever by the way, was making terrible ravages here a few weeks since, and no adequate measures taken to combat it."  Judicial reform talked about  Nabk: issue of corrupt officials, difficult to prove etc. The Kaimakam of Dūmā will probably soon be tried in Damascus   "The rather evident anti-Turk sentiment and prejudice, which began to appear throughout Syria some eighteen months ago has gone on simmering, and nearly reached boiling point perhaps after speeches of the deputy Assali [Shukrī al-ʿAsalī] (who is popular among Arabs), and certain remarks on the numbers of employés in the Ministry of Finance among whom the Arabs reckon less than one per cent. The Union + Progress Committees have certainly within this district been dwindling and losing influence and less + less attended by parties generally esteemed for their patriotism + capacities, for fully a year past and are now a mere shadow. A large party was to have been delegated + sent from Salonica, for the restoration of Union + Progress influence and allaying any sore feelings on the part of Arabs; this drew forth adverse criticism on the part of certain local newspapers, which again was answered by a reminder that such attitude was far from polite + &lt;tei:del&gt;quite out of accord with&lt;/tei:del&gt; unworthy of  Arab repute for hospitality + welcome to visitors. The project, I hear, is now suspended at least for several months. But occasional visitors have been here lately including  of the Turkish Foreign Office, and others from  Salonica.  Army officers continue to exercise their men zealously + regularly ; and troops have been much moved about during the past three months; eight battalions of the Army Corps went to serve in Yemen. One notes the presence of non-Moslem soldiers about Damascus; of whom there may be some 1500 to be observed, and at one time so many as 500 together attended the Armenian Cathedral Church.  Harvests + fruit crops have been good here and business was lively."  Rumours of imminent exchange of Valis, Vali of Aleppo is said to replace , who is destined for Adana or Angora.  PS: inclosing a report of M Mishāqa, the US dragoman and son of Nāṣīf Mishāqa, the British pro-consul&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1913-02-18" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/muqtabas+561-eap">Jarīdat al-muqtabas 18 Feb 1913 (#1119)&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;1 article on the Zionists  3m: today celebrations of the mawlid nabawī  m: demonstration of the poor against the high prices of bread  yest gather a large crowd (jamm ghafīr) of poor on account of the high price of bread, a raṭl of which reach Ps 4"20. they stage the demonstration and shouted outside the offices of the deputy president of the municipality. after a while, he came out and led the crowd to the offices of the deputy Vali calling for orders to prohibit exports of wheat and flour outside the province. this had been granted by the MoI and the cabinet in Istanbul  took the relevant measures to stop all exports  the baladiyya called on the millers and bakers and extended the pricing of bread and flour. this will inshaallah decrease the prices and ease the fate of the poor who also suffer from the lack of work due to the war-induced recession.  after this was written the baladiyya  brought the bakers and millers to set the price of a raṭl of bread to Ps 3"20 to Ps 4 and announced this measure in the Suqs. the bakeries were monitored until everyone adhered to the new prices  &lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1917--" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/Grobba+1917">PA AA Damaskus 8 Jerusalem K.Nr. 154 / J.Nr. 2252, Anlage 1, vertraulich, Grobba, "Bericht über die diesjährige Getreideernte im Bezirk der Etappeninspektion Jerusalem", 1917&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;# Abschrift, Vertraulich, Bericht über die diesjährige Getreideernte im Bezirk der Etappeninspektion Jerusalem, .- mentions inter alia Ruppin’s book- long report on amounts of grain / cereals harvested in 1917 by Kaza: wheat ("staff of life"), barley and vetches / Wicken (fodder), lentils and broad beans / Saubohnen  (dried vegetables)- places: Jerusalem, Kerak, Beirut"Der Etappeninspektion Jerusalem unterstehen1. Der selbstständige Regierungsbezirk Jerusalem2. im  Ostjordanlande die westliche Hälfte des Reg.Bezirks Kerak, d.h. vom Kreise Salt der Zentral-Amtsbezirk und der Amtsbezirk Madeba, ferner der Zentralkreis von Kerak.## Bestellte Fläche### 1. Jerusalem[...]" [...]Auffällig ist das ständige Abnehmen der bebauten Fläche während des Krieges. Die Gründe sind teils wirtschaftliche, die durch den Krieg hervorgerufen sind, teils militärische.Es mangelt den Fellachen an Saatgetreide, Arbeitern und Tieren. Die noch vorhandenen Arbeiter sind meist Deserteure. Ohne sie wäre die Lage noch schlimmer.Die Fellachen können ihre Ernte der Kontrolle der Regierung nicht entziehen. Sie mussten  im Gegensatz zu den Landwirten des Ostjordanlandes den Zehnten in Natura entrichten und ausserdem zwangsweise an die Etappe 35% vom  und 50% von der verkaufen, so dass ihnen nur etwa die Hälfte der Ernte vom Weizen und noch weniger von der Gerste verblieb. Nun hatten die Fellachen meist zur Zeit der Aussaat kein Saatgetreide gehabt und sich dieses gegen Gold zu hohem Preise kaufen müssen. ; die zum Besäen eines Dönüm benötigten ¾ Tabbe hatte als ¾ Ltq gekostet. Die durchschnittliche Ernte betrugt 10 tabbe pro Dönüm. Davon mussten als Zehnt 1¼ Tabbe und gegen geringe Bezahlen etwa 3 Tabbe, im ganzen also etwa 4¼ Tabbe abgegeben werden. Von de ihm verbleibenden 5¾ Tabbe Weizen musste der Fellach etwa 4 verkaufen, um das zur Aussaat geliehene ¾ Goldpfund zurückzuzahlen. Es verblieben im somit nur 1¾ Tabbe, von denen er wieder ¾ Tabbe für die Aussaat reservieren musste. So rentiert sich schliesslich für viele Fellachen die Bebauung   ihres Landes nicht mehr, und sie zogen es vor, es brach liegen zu lassen. Trotzdem zeigen die Kazas Jaffa und Hebron im letzten Jahre noch ein Zunehmen der bestellten Fläche. In den Kazas Birseba und Gaza, von denen erhebliche Teile sich in den Händen des Feindes befinden, is natürlich die bestellte Fläche aus diesem Grunde erheblich kleiner als im vergangenen Jahre.### 2. Reg.Bezirk Kerak, a. Kaza Salt[...] Das entspricht der Tatsache: Seit 2 Jahren besäht man im Ostjordanland soviel Land wie nur irgend möglich. Die bestellte Fläche im Kaza Salt hat seit dem vorigen Jahre schätzungsweise um 20% zugenommen. Der Kaza Salt umfasst folgende Amtsbezirke: 1. Salt selbst,2. Amman,3. Madeba, 4. Dschize.Von diesen gehören zum Bezirke der Etappeninspektion Jerusalem Salt und Madeba. [...]Beni-Sachr  und Hamaidi-Beduinen [...]Die Erne schätzt man dieses Jahr im Ostjordanland bei geringem Boden auf ein etwa 5 faches, bei mittlerem auf ein 7-8 faches, auf sehr gutem Boden bis zum 25 fachen. [...]### 2. Reg.Bezirk Kerak, b. Kaza Kerak [...], davon der  der [sic] Teil Jerusalems [...]Die Gründe dafür, dass im Gegensatz zum Westjordanlande im Osten die bestellte Fläche im Kriege und insbesondere im letzten Jahre zugenommen hat, sind folgende:1. Die Einwohner des Reg.Bez. Kerak sind vom Militärdienst befreit (teils als Beduinen, teils vielleicht auch wegen Misstrauens der Regierung). Daher mangelt es ihnen nicht an Arbeitern. Auch viele Deserteure verstecken sich drüben und helfen bei der Arbeit. Tiere hat man bei den Leuten im Ostjordanlande gleichfalls nicht wie im Westen requirieren können, da insbesondere die Beduinen ihre Tiere stets rechtzeitig verstecken.2. Im vergangenen Jahre hat die Regierung den Zehnten im Osten (um Gegensatz zum Westen) in Papiergeld einkassiert. Es fanden auch keine Zwangskäufe statt. Die Landleute und Beduinen versteckten sofort ihre Ernte in von Fremden unauffindbaren Zisternen. Als dann , öffneten sie diese Zisternen heimlich eine nach der anderen und verkauften das Getreide. Die Armee, die vorher unterlassen hatte, die benötigte Menge zu beschlagnahmen, und die Getreidekommission Jerusalem sahen sich genötigt, die geforderten Preise zu bezahlen. Die Landwirte im Osten (meist Grossgrundbesitzer und Beduinen) waren auch zur Zeit der Aussaat nicht genötigt gewesen, Saatgetreide gegen Gold zu kaufen, und brauchten daher dieses Gold nicht mit Zinsen zurückzugeben. 3. Die Regierung in Kerak hätte vielleicht anfangs durch Energie die Leute zur Annahme von Papiergeld zwingen können. Da aber in Kerak binnen der kritischen Zeit vier verschiedene Mutessarifs waren, so fehlte es an jedem zielbewussten Handeln der Regierung. Es scheint sogar, als ob die Regierungsbeamten in Reg.Bez. Kerak die Bereicherung der dortigen Einwohner aus nicht uneigennützigen Beweggründen fördern. Sie selbst kaufen übrigens den meisten Weizen für die Regierung auf. Sobald aber die Rede ist von Monopolisierung des Ankaufs durch die Etappe oder eine Kommission, so treten sie stets lebhaft für den Freihandel ein und bekämpfen heimlich Etappe oder Einkaufskommission.[...]Obwohl  der Zehnt im Osten in Natur erhoben und ein zweiter Zehnt zwangsweise ( - gegenüber ) gekauft wird, so is auch bereits das Verstecken der Ernte im vollen Gange. Die Beni Sachr- und Hamaidi-Beduinen bezahlen übrigens auch in diesem Jahre den Zehnten nur eigenem Gutdünken.## Geschätzte Ernte: Jerusalem[...][...]Gemäss Z.5. haben die Wilajets von Bezirken mit geringeren Ernten darüber zu entscheiden, ob für die Armee gekauft werden soll oder nicht. Demgemäss ist für den Reg.Bez. Jerusalem entschieden worden, dass ausser dem geschuldeten Zehnt kein weiterer, dass dagegen von der Gerste 2 weitere Zehnt angekauft werden sollen. Der fehlende zweite Weizenzehnt muss aus den Jerusalem zu diesem Zweck überlassenen Nachbarbezirken , , , , , , , ,  beschafft werden. [...][...] Die Etappe hat aber voriges Jahr den von ihr vom Bezirk Jerusalem, vom Ostjordanland oder von Norden bezogenen Weizen nicht sämtlich den Truppen gegeben, sondern erhebliche Mengen an die Bevölkerung von Jerusalem verkauft. So hat die von dem Büro der Nationalen Verteidigung gebildete Kommission in der Zeit vom 1. Januar bis 10. Juli 1916 1668814 kg, das Getreidesyndikat des Bankdirektors Mareks in der Zeit vom 11. Juli - 31. Oktober 1916 1712722 kg im ganzen 3381536 kg erhalten. Ausserdem hat sie noch mehrere Hunderttausend kg an einzelne Private verkauft.Die Gesamternte der Etappeninspektion Jerusalem kann man nach dem oben Aufgeführten also folgendermassen schätzen:### 1. Reg.Bezirk Jerusalem[...] [...]### 2. Reg.Bezirk Kerak[...] [...]  [...]## [missing heading]"Den täglichen Bedarf der IV. Armee bei Schätzung auf 300000 Köpfe und einem  berechnet die hiesige Etappe auf 150 t Weizen, 180 t Viehfutter und 45 t Gemüse. Das ergibt ein Jahresbedürfnis von 54750 t Weizen, 65700 t Viehfutter und 16425 t Gemüse."[...]Die Walis haben daher freie Ankäufe von Getreide vorgesehen und in Z.6. die Preise festgesetzt, die natürlich in Papier gemeint sind. Da bekanntlich für Papier im allgemeinen ohne Gewalt niemand Getreide verkauft, hat sich die Etappeninspektion Jerusalem bereits veranlasst gesehen,  zu zahlen. Aber auch dafür erhält sie nichts, obwohl , also geringer als 1 Pi Gold und 3 Pi. Papier ist. Eine grosse Menge Gold zu bekommen, dürfte aber wohl kaum der Etappeninspektion Jerusalem gelingen, und eine solche Massnahme wäre auch wirtschaftlich sehr zu beklagen. Das vorhandene Gold wird die Etappeninspektion ganz zur Bezahlung der Transportlöhne der Beduinen benötigen. Um nun noch eine grössere Menge Getreide ohne Gold zu bekommen zu können gibt es nur ein Mittel, nämlich die Einziehung eines dritten Zehnten gegen Bezahlung."[...][...]"Die Ernährung der Zivilbevölkerung der in dem der Etappeninspektion Jerusalem unterstehenden Gebiete wird sich in diesem Jahre voraussichtlich folgendermassen gestalten:Die Einwohnerzahl beträgt nach amtlichen Angaben der (Nefusbüros)^[Die Listen der Nefus-Büros sind nicht vollständig. Etwa 20% der Bevölkerung sind nicht eingetragen. Ebensohoch ist der in letzter Zeit erfolgte Abgang an Ausgewanderten, Verbannten, Toten einzuschätzen, die noch nicht registriert sind. Daher mögen die amtlichen Zahlen zur Zeit etwa richtig sein.]  im[Ort] | [Einwohner]-|-- Reg.Bezirk Jerusalem: | 393796    + Kreis Jerusalem | 121773    + Kreis Jaffa | 81492    + Kreis Gaza | 82864    + Kreis Hebron | 57667    + Kreis Birseba (eigene Schätzung) | 50000 - Reg.Bezirk Kerak (Stand im Jahre 1915 nach amtlichen Angaben, eingezogen von Dr. Ruppin, s.S.8 seines Buches): | 64536    + Kreis Kerak | 195551    + Kreis Salt | 37235    + Kreis Tafile | 7750- Reg.Bezirk Nablus: | 153749    + Kreis Nablus | 76426    + Kreis Jenin | 41422    + Kreis Beni Saab | 35901- im ganzen: | 612081. Daher beträgt der Tagesbedarf obiger Bevölkerung 153020 kg, der Jahresbedarf 58852300 kg [should be 55852391,25 kg] Getreide."[...][...]Bleiben für die Bevölkerung 63030000 kg.Der Bedarf ist also gedeckt.Bei dieser Berechnung ist aber als Bedarf der Bevölkerung nur Brotgetreide (zu 250 g pro Kopf täglich) berücksichtigt, während bei dem zur Verfügung stehenden Getreide Brotgetreide, Futter und Gemüse gleichwertig berechnet worden ist.Unter Berücksichtigung von Brotgetreide (Weizen und Dari) allein ist die Lage folgende:[...]Fehlbetrag 7084300 kgDieser Fehlbetrag kann nicht aus dem Wilajet Damaskus gedeckt werden; denn gemäss Berechnung Konsul Loytveds () ergibt sich bei mittlerer Ernte (und eine solche haben wir höchstens) bereits, wenn das Militär auch nur 2/8 der Ernte nimmt ein Fehlbetrag von 46490 t.Auch im Wilajet Aleppo dürfte kaum ein Überschuss an Weizen vorhanden sein, da die dortige Ernte nur die Hälfte der vorjährigen betragen soll. Der Preis des Brotes war dort vor etwa einem Monat fast das dreifach des Jerusalemer Preises."- shortages in the Vilayet of Aleppo. Harvests are only half of those of the previous year. prices reached three times those of Jerusalem.- lack of means of transport from Aleppo would further prevent any supplies from there - 250 gr are insufficient: "Dann ist zu beachten, dass  zwar mehr ist, als auf den Kopf jetzt in Deutschland kommt, dass es aber für die hiesige Bevölkerung, der Brot die Hauptsache ist, nicht genügt.Unter dem Getreidemangel werden die kleineren Städte und Dörfer nicht so sehr leiden, da die dortigen Einwohner in Gemüse und Obst gute und billige Nahrung finden, insbesondere sind in diesem Jahre die Kaktusfeigen und Weintrauben sehr reichlich. Die Einwohner der grösseren Städte, insbesondere von Jerusalem werden aber voraussichtlich sehr leiden, noch mehr als schon im vergangenen Jahre. Der Getreidemangel wird hier vergrössert werden durch den Mangel an Transportmitteln, an Gold und an Organisation überhaupt.Die Etappe gibt den Getreidehandel erst frei, wenn sie die ihr zukommende Menge erhalten hat. Da die Abschätzung und die Abnahme dieser Menge aber langsam vonstatten geht, können bis zur Freigabe des Handels noch 2 bis 3 Monate vergehen, gerade die kostbarste Zeit, . Sobald aber das Dreschen beendet ist, verstecken es die Besitzer in Zisternen und holen es nur gegen viel höhere Preise wieder hervor.Es wird ungemein schwierig sein, das zum Ankauf erforderliche Geld  aufzubringen. Zum Ankauf des Jahresbedarfs ist fast 1 Million Ltq Gold nötig, zum Transport weitere 300000 Ltq, und das bei Annahme, dass der Preis so niedrig bleibt. Eine Folge der Getreidenachfrage wird sein, dass das Gold immer teurer wird.  und wird bald das 5 fach kosten (Mitte Juli kostet das Gold bereits mehr als das 5 fache). Um nun hier Abhülfe zu schaffen, ist von den Behörden folgendes beschlossen worden:"[...]  [...] "Die Bestechlichkeit der Kontrollbeamten ist augenblicklich ein Segen für die Bevölkerung.In letzter Zeit ist ein erheblicher Teil der Ernte des Kreises Salt durch die  und -Beduinen vernichtet oder gestohlen worden.Der Anlass zu dem feindseligen Verhalten dieser gab die unmotivierte Erschiessung eines  durch einen Gendarmen aus Madeba. Infolge dessen umlauerten die Beni-Sachr in Stärke von 30 mit modernen Gewehren bewaffneten Mann Tag und Nacht die Stadt Madeba, um an dem Gendarmen Rache zu nehmen. Zugleich trieben sie ihre Tiere in die Felder der Madebaer. Diese scheinen sich dann losgekauft zu haben, denn eine Zeit lang wurden ihre Felder geschont. Die Feindseligkeit begann aber wieder. Am 25. Juni kam es zum Gefecht zwischen etwa 30-40 Beni-Sachr auf der einen und -Beduinen nebst einigen Madebaern auf er anderen Seite. 2 S'char und 1 Eduan sollen getroffen sein. Der Grund zu diesem Gefechte war wieder ein Einfall der Beni-Sachr in Madebaergebiet, gegen den sich die Besitzer auf Rat des Kaimakams von Salt mit Waffen wehrten.Die Beni Sachr und die Hamaidi weigern sich, den Zehnten bei ihnen abschätzen zu lassen oder ihn zu bezahlen. Der Kaimakam von Salt wagt nicht gegen sie Gewalt anzuwenden und wäre auch, selbst wenn er es wollte, machtlos. So wird der Ausfall an Zehnten ein ganz bedeutender sein, allerdings trifft dieser Ausfall vor allem die östliche Hälfte des Reg.Bez. Kerak. Abhilfe kann nur dadurch geschaffen werden, wenn Truppen, möglichst Kavallerie in jene Gegend gelegt werden.Der frühere  hatte das bereits beschlossen, ist aber dann durch seine Versetzung davon abgekommen.Die Beni Sachr und die Hamaidi haben sich auch in früheren Jahren regierungsfeindlich gezeigt, doch nicht in dem Masse wie in diesem Jahre. Es scheint als ob sie in englischem Solde stehen. Dieser Verdacht wird noch dadurch verstärkt, dass sie es lieben, den Türken ungünstige Gerüchte zu verbreiten. So erzählten sie kürzlich, der Scherif von Mekka sei im Anmarsch und bereits in der Nähe, sodass in Madeba Aufregung entstand. Die Beni Sachr und Hamaidi können mit den Engländern im Irak und wahrscheinlich auch im Hedschaz ungehindert verkehren.Jetzt fordern die Beni Sachr von allem aus Madeba gehenden . Die in der Gegend von Madeba sitzenden Belka-Beduinen beanspruchen diesen Tribut für sich. Zwischen beiden ist es schon mehrfach zu Schiessereien gekommen und es hat auf beiden Seiten schon eine ganze Reihe Tote gegeben. Die Beni Sachr bringen zur Zeit ihre Familien und ihre Getreide östlich der  in Sicherheit und werden dann wieder kommen um einen am  erschossenen Scheich zu rächen. Die Lage ist in den letzten Tagen, seit das VIII. Armeekorps in Amman liegt, etwas besser. Man lässt aber trotzdem die Beni Sachr ruhig mit ihren Kamelen und ihrem Getreide abziehen.Es ist schon ein erheblicher Teil der Ernte drüben verloren gegangen. Die Weizenpreise steigen. Jeder sucht seine Ernte möglichst schnell zu verstecken. Die Grossgrundbesitzer, die im vorigen Jahre viel Gold eingenommen haben, verkaufen selbst um hohe Preise nicht, da sie sicher damit rechnen können, dass die Preise dieses Jahr noch viel höher steigen werden, als vergangenes Jahr.Es ist also nicht zu leugnen, dass die Ernährungslage der Bevölkerung im Bezirke der Etappeninspektion Jerusalem und insbesondere in dieser  Stadt sehr ernst wird.Das Getreide reicht aus, wenn die augenblickliche  und  bestehen bleibt und der sich so ergebende Überschuss der Bevölkerung zugute kommt, wird sie aber - und das ist natürlich um Interesse der Truppen nötig - wieder auf  und  erhöht, so genügt das vorhandene Getreide nicht für die Bevölkerung und es muss in Jerusalem zu Hungerkrisen kommen.Eine ganze oder teilweise Evakuierung Jerusalems wird dann nicht zu vermeiden sein."gez. GrobbaOberleutnant&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1917-04-02" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/Damaskus2Apr1917+1917">PA AA Damaskus 8 Damaskus K.Nr. 381, Anlage, N.N., 2 Apr 1917&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;# Damaskus, 2 Apr 1917, Anlage- specifying amounts of wheat / cereals needed for the supply of the troops and the civilian population by district. prices are not immediately decipherable"Die Brodfrage ist auch in dem als gr[...] bekannt Wilayet Syrien  (Damaskus) mit der "[...] die übrigen ¾ sollen der Zivilbevölkerung bleiben. [...]Sandschak (Regierungsbezirk) | ha-|-Hama | 150000Damaskus | 100000Hauran mit Drusengebirge | 175000Kerak | 85000[Summe] | 510000[...]1. Saatgut + 200 kg Weizen Saat für jeden ha + 120 kg Gersten Saat für jeden ha2. ErtragfähigkeitGetreide | Ernte ||-| gute | mittlere | geringebei Weizen | 10 | 6 | 4 fachebei Gerste | 12 | 8 | 5 fache[...]Es könnte also auch bei guter Ernte das für die Bevölkerung [...] Weizenbedarf der auf 100000 t geschäzt wird, [...] &lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1918-03-16" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/Schulenburg+1918d">PA AA Damaskus 8 Damaskus J.Nr. 342, Schulenburg, 16 Mar 1918&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;# Damaskus, J.Nr. 342, 16 Mar 1918,  to , Ambassador in Constantinople- two attachments: Erlass vom 23. Januar d.J. - II 474 -Sending a copy of Dr. Zellner's draft of a plan to increase the production of wheat, barley, and Durrah in Syria ("Entwurf eines Planes zur Hebung der Produktion von Weizen, Gerste und Durrha in Syrien"). The author deems the plan illusionary as Syria isn't governed by a European power and points to various omissions / errors in Zellner's plan, namely that already in times of peace Syria had imported wheat from overseas. The area of land under the plough has decreased and the state collects at least ⅛ of cereals in taxes and another ⅛ in forced sales at set prices. Half the conscripted men have deserted and returned to their homes and toil the fields. The suggestion to employ soldiers for fieldwork cannot be implemented. In addition there exist no comprehensive lists of conscripted soldiers, their trades etc. "Die Ernährungsschwierigkeiten Syrien's [sic] sind bekannt; sie sind im Laufe des Krieges immer schlimmer geworden und drohen sich nunmehr zu einer Katastrophe auszuwachsen .""Herr Zeller glaubt, dass es Listen der Landarbeiter in der Armee und über die Bevölkerung in den einzelnen Bezirken gibt. Ich nehme bestimmt an, dass solche Listen nicht vorhanden sind; sollte dies trotzdem der Fall sein, so sind die Zusammenstellungen sicher gefälscht. ""Die Ernährungsfrage ist hier in der allerletzten Zeit in ein ganz kritisches Stadium getreten.  habe ich auf anderem Wege gemeldet, dass  () betragen hatte, innerhalb weniger Tage  war. In den letzten tagen hat ein neuer gewaltiger Sprung nach oben stattgefunden: . Derartige Preise bedeuten Hungersnot für den ärmeren Teil der Bevölkerung, der sich mit Vorräten bis zur neuen Ernte nicht hat versehen können. Es scheint, dass auch die Depots der Regierung leer sind, sodass selbst die Ernährung der Armee ernstlich in Frage gestellt sein würde.Die Schuld an dieser riesigen und plötzlichen Preissteigerung ist von der öffentlichen Meinung zunächst den Getreideankäufen in die Schuhe geschoben worden, die die deutsche Etappe der Heeresgruppe F hier vorgenommen hat. Es ist richtig, dass die Etappe hier Getreide gekauft und über den Marktpreis bezahlt hat. Sie ist bei der Auswahl ihrer Aufkäufer nicht vorsichtig genug gewesen und diese haben sich ungeschickt und betrügerisch benommen, Im ganzen hat die Etappe aber, so weit ich habe ermitteln können, nur wenig über 300 Tonnen gekauft und die Aufkäufe bereits vor 2 Monaten eingestellt. Es liegt also auf der Hand, dass die 300 von deutscher Seite und vor längerer Zeit gekauften Tonnen Getreide die Preisverhältnisse auf dem sehr bedeutenden Damaszener Markt nicht tief berühren und keines Falles eine Preissteigerung wie geschehen herbeiführen  können. Ich habe deshalb den Wali gebeten, den hier umlaufenen Gerüchten, wonach die Deutschen an der Steigerung der Getreidepreise schuld seien, in der Presse entgegen zu treten. Ein daraufhin in der hiesigen Zeitung "Esch Schark" [al-Sharq] veröffentlichter Leitartikel ist in französischer Uebersetzung ganz ergebenst beigefügt. Der Wali beabsichtigte, einen ähnlichen Artikel in der amtlichen Zeitung "Surija" [Sūriye] zu veröffentlichen, ich habe aber geglaubt, davon abraten zu sollen, um der Sache nicht allzugrosse Bedeutung beizulegen. Der wahre Grund für die plötzliche Steigerung der hiesigen Getreidepreise scheint darin zu liegen, dass die Drusen  im Dschebel Drus, die einzigen, die noch über bedeutende Getreidevorräte verfügen, von hiesigen Spekulanten angestiftet worden sind, mit ihren Zufuhren nach Damaskus aufzuhören. Im Hauran sind grösserer Vorräte nicht mehr vorhanden. Der grosse Djemal Pascha hatte nach der vorigen Ernte wohl den Drusen, nicht aber den Hauranesen gestattet, Getreide nach Damaskus auszuführen. Er hoffte auf diese Weise den Heeresbedarf an Getreide billig im Hauran zu erhalten. Die Folge aber ist gewesen, dass die Hauranesen ihre gesamten Vorräte an die Drusen verkauft haben.Der Notlage abzuhelfen sehe ich nur drei Wege:1. _Stärkere Heranziehung der im Drusengebirge noch vorhandenen reichlichen Vorräte._ Da die Drusen von der türkischen Regierung tatsächlich unabhängig sind und da infolgedessen Zwang nicht angewandt werden kann, kann auf diesem Wege ein Erfolg nur erreicht werden, wenn sehr grosse Mittel in Gold zur Verfügung gestellt werden.2. _Stärkere Zufuhren von Norden_ (aus dem Gebiete von Konia oder gar Russland), die sich vielleicht ermöglichen liessen, falls die Leistungsfähigkeit der Eisenbahn durch Zuführung von Steinkohle als Heizmaterial entsprechend erhöht werden könnte.3. _Vergrösserung der Anbaufläche._ Da die türkische Beamtenschaft weder geändert noch beiseite geschoben werden kann, erscheint es aussichtslos, dass der Bauer zu stärkerem Anbau bewogen werden könnte. Dagegen wäre es an sich möglich, vorhandene weite und fruchtbare Landstriche mit Dampf- oder Motorpflügen zu bestellen. Eine ganze Anzahl Dampfpflüge sollen in der Gegend von Adana unbenützt herumstehen. Ein derartiges Unternehmen würde aber nur dann Aussicht auf Erfolge haben, wenn es deutscherseits in die Hand genommen würde und wenn die deutsche Leitung das Recht erhielte, die geeigneten Arbeiter aus den Deserteuren  (alle arbeitsfähigen Männer, die nicht in der Front stehen sind Deserteure) selbst herauszusuchen und mit Bescheinigungen (Wessikas) zu versehen, die sie vor Zugriffen der der [sic] türkischen Behörden schützen. Bei einer derartigen Ordnung der Angelegenheit würde die türkische Beamtenschaft nichts verdienen. Die deutsche Leitung würde infolgedessen selbstverständlich gegen die wütendsten Chikanen [sic] zu kämpfen haben.–Durch ein Beschreiten des Weges zu 1. &amp; 2. würde an sich verhätlinismässig rasch eine Besserung der hiesigen Ernährungslage erreicht werden können. Der Weg zu 3., auf dem eine ganze Anzahl Vorarbeiten unvermeidlich sind, könnt erst nach einiger Zeit zum Ziele führen.-Im gegenwärtigen Augenblicke tut schnelle Hilfe, not denn in den nächsten 3 Monaten, d.h. bis zur Ernte, ist nicht zu erwarten, dass von selbst eine Besserung der Lage eintritt. Der Mangel an Getreide und die hohen Preise haben bereits zu kleinen Revolten vor den Bäckerläden geführt. (). Die Armee soll nur noch 250 g Brot für den Mann und den Tag erhalten, eine Menge, die nicht genügt, den einfachen Soldaten, der so gut wie nichts anderes zu essen bekommt, bei zu Kräften zu erhalten. Aus der schlechten Ernährung erklären sich die vielen Desertionen und daraus wieder die ausserordentliche Schwäche der türkischen Gefechtsstärke, die dem Gegner das Spiel so leicht macht.-Der hiesige Wali, dem das gesamte Verpflegungswesen Syriens, sowohl das für die Armee wie das für die Zivilbevölkerung untersteht, hat sich unter diesen Umständen entschlossen, den Weg zu beschreiten, der theoretisch die schnellste Abhilfe verspricht. Er will sich in den nächsten Tagen nach Deraa begeben und versuchen, grössere Getreidemengen aus dem Hauran und dem Drusengebirge schleunigst nach Damaskus zu leiten. Ich glaube nicht, dass der Wali grossen Erfolg haben wird. Der Hauran kann keine nennenswerten Mengen Getreide mehr liefern und die Drusen werden sich  schwer hüten, dir Früchte ihrer Spekulation aufzugeben. Sie werden Ausflüchte machen und hintertreiben, dass schnell grosse Mengen von Getreide nach Damaskus kommen. So wird es besten Falles gelingen, die hiesigen Lebensmittelpreise (wie es immer und überall der Fall ist, sind die Preise der übrigen Nahrungsmittel dem Steigen der Brotpreise gefolgt) ein wenig herabzudrücken, gewiss aber nicht soweit, dass dem armen Teil des Volkes wirklich geholfen wäre. Ich fürchte, dass die nächsten 3 Monate für die Bevölkerung Syriens traurige sein werden.Ueber die neue Ernte denkt der hiesige Wali sehr optimistisch. Er nimmt als sicher an, dass sie gut werden und dass er aus dem Wilajet Damaskus , aus dem Wilajet Aleppo  und aus dem Wilajet Beirut  Getreide erhalten wird. Er meint allerdings dass &lt;tei:del&gt;zur Beschaffung&lt;/tei:del&gt; zum Ankauf  dieser Mengen die Verausgabung von 1000000 Ltq. Gold nötig werden wird. Ich glaube  unter keinen Umständen  daran, dass die genannten Mengen Getreide werden aufgebracht werden können. Die Ernteaussichten sind augenblicklich  allerdings günstige, günstigere als im Vorjahre. Aus den Gründen, die ich oben geschildert habe (Verringerung der Anbaufläche u.s.w.) wird trotzdem der Ausfall im kommenden Wirtschaftsjahre grösser werden als im alten. Die neue Ernte wird mit höheren Anfangspreise realisiert werden müssen als die des  Vorjahres () und im Lauf der Zeit werden die Preise noch höher steigen als diesmal. Es erscheint mir daher nötig, dass sobald wie möglich auch das Beschreiten der zu 2. &amp; 3. [sic] geschilderten Wege (Stärkere  Zufuhren von Norden und Bestellung von Brachland mit Dampfpflügen) ins Auge gefasst wird. Im Hinblick auf den Widerstand, dem die Ausgaben grosser Mengen Gold in Syrien begegnen muss, und auf die grossen Schwierigkeiten, die der Erhöhung der Eisenbahnleistung entgegenstehen, wird es sich meines Erachtens nicht umgehen lassen, auch den Weg zu 3. einzuschlagen, wenn der Krieg in Syrien im Jahre 1919 fortgesetzt werden soll."&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1918-03-17" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/LaChéretéDesVivres+1918">PA AA Damaskus 8 Damaskus, N.N., "La chéreté des vivres", 17 Mar 1918&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;# La chéreté des vivres, 17 Mar 1918**Reporting a feared food riot**- only two days ago, the raṭl of bread was sold at Ps 32-34- yesterday, the price rose to Ps 45 / raṭl- consequently there are many arguments in all roads and the bakeries "Jusqu'a deux jours avant, on vendait à Damas . Hier . A la suite de cette hausse, dans toutes les rues et toutes les boulangéries de la ville, il ya un des disputes et des querelles. On a meme commencé à attaquer les boulangeries et à prendre le pain par force. Aucune mésure n'a été prise pour empecher ce désordre. Aujour'hui encore le prix reste le meme, de plus, toute sort de légume et de vivres a suivi le prix du pain. Jusqu'a ce moment, je ne sais pais quelles sont les mésures que les Autorités Locales ont l'intention du prendre, au moins pour apraiser l'agigation du public.Quelques commercants veullent croise que cette hausse a été caussée par l'achat des fournisseurs des troupes Allemandes des grandes quantités du blé aux prix réclamés par les commercants des céréales, sans avoir marchandé suivant l'usage du pays.Mais ce que je peux comprendre  de cet état de choses, est que les Druks [?] chez qui les grandes quantités du blé se trouvent actuellement, avaient céssé **dépuis quelques jours** d'envoyer du blé à Damas, rien que par malice pour créer une hausse éxhorbitante au prix. On peut dire meme, que cette mésure infernale a été prise en commun accord avec **quelques gros spéculateurs déguises**.Je dois noter que lors de la dernière récolte les Ducks [?] ont réussi - grace à l'aide du grand Djémal Pacha - d'acheter des trés fortes quantités du blé de Horanais à un prix trés modéré - car, à ce tempo la, il n'etait permais qu'aux Druks [?] d'importer des céréales à Damas - Ce fait a résulté le mécontement générale à Horan, et avait résulté alors quelques révoltes suivies par l'éxécution d'un certain nombre des Horanais, et maintenant, la population de Damas souffrant des conséquances."17-3-18signature (illegible)&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
    <event start="1918-08-29" title="Food riot">
        &lt;a xmlns:till="http://www.sitzextase.de" xmlns:tss="http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/SenteXML-1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" href="sente://BachBibliographie/Brode+1918a">PA AA Damaskus 8 Damaskus J.Nr. 1766 draft, Brode, 29 Aug 1918&lt;/a>
        &lt;p&gt;# Damaskus 1766 draft, 29 Aug 1918&lt;/p&gt;
        </event>
</data>